<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY mdash "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
]>

<chapter id="chap_editingpubs">
  <!-- $Id: EditingPublications.xml,v 1.5 2005/01/15 17:10:58 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Editing Publications</title>

  <section id="editpubsintro">
    <title>Editing Publications</title>

    <para>Instances of a publication type, for instance News items as shown in the
    tutorial, are created and edited in the Edit window. This window consists
    of two main parts&mdash;the publication specific fields, as defined by the
    system administrator, and the meta data defined by Pagesetter. The
    publication fields part looks somewhat like this:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Editing publications - user data</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubEditData.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>What you see is three different fields defined by the administrator
    of the web site. It is up to you to write whatever you find fitting for
    your kind of publication&mdash;in this case a News item describing some of
    the pleasantries of hiking Bornholm.</para>

    <para>The meta data fields looks like below.</para>
    
    <figure>
      <title>Editing publications - meta data</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubEditMetaData.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>


  <section id="editpubsinformation">
    <title>Publish information</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Approval state</term>

        <listitem>
          The approval state is an information about where the
          publication is located in the associated workflow. The possible
          states depends on the workflow setup, but the standard workflows
          uses states like "Preview" and "Approved" to denote the fact that
          the publication is ready for preview (by an editor) or actually
          approved by the moderator. The approval state can only be changed by
          one of the workflow actions available at the bottom of the
          page.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Online setting</term>

        <listitem>
          This field indicates whether the publication is online or not,
          and thereby if it is visible on any of the publication lists or can
          be found by searching.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Publish Date</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This setting specifies the first day a publication goes
          online. Normally this value is left empty, but you can get Pagesetter
          to insert the current date for you. This feature is enabled in the
          general configuration section ("Auto fill publish date").</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Expire Date</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This setting specifies the day a publication goes offline (it
          will not be available at the specified day).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="editpubslocation">
    <title>Location</title>

    <para>These settings categorizes the publication and defines where to find
    it.<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Topic</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The PostNuke topic in which the publication belongs.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Show in lists</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies whether or not the publication should be shown in
            the general list of this publication type. This can be usefull if
            you want some publications to be accessible through a menu or
            handcrafted URL only.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Language</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The language in which the publication is written. The
            language influences when the publication shows up in the various
            lists and menus. The language must match the user's language in
            order to show up&mdash;or be set to "All".</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="editpubsauthor">
    <title>Author Information</title>

    <para>These settings holds who has written the publication and
    when.<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Publisher</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The PostNuke user name of the user who created the
            publication. This name cannot be changed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Author</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the publication author. The creator's real name
            is inserted here - but may at any later time be changed to
            something else.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Created</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The date of creation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Last updated</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Last updated date.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="editpubssetting">
    <title>Setting Editor Defaults</title>

    <para>It is possible to assign defaults for new publications via the URL
    as shown in the <link linkend="chap_linking">linking
    chapter</link>.</para>
  </section>

  </section>
</chapter>