<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap_extratools">
  <!-- $Id: ExtraTools.xml,v 1.3 2005/01/15 17:10:58 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Extra Tools</title>

  <section id="extraimport">
    <title>Importing Data</title>

    <para>Pagesetter offers a small set of tools to import data from other modules.
    You find these tools in the Tools::Import menu link which will take you to the 
    window shown below.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Various import tools.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/import.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="importnews">
    <title>Importing From PostNuke News</title>

    <para>Pagesetter offers the possibility to import all of your existing
    news items into a new publication type. Select Tools::Import from the menu.
    Then click on the "Import News" button and you are done! You can check the
    "Add image field" in order to get a selectable image and image text
    associated with your news items.</para>

    <caution>If you have many (really many) news items then you may
    have trouble doing the import in the time allocated for your PHP script on
    the web server. If you have any influence on this factor then make sure
    your script have enough time. Otherwise, just try and see what happens, it
    probably works.</caution>

    <para>The new publication type will be named PN-News, comes with a full
    set of predefined templates named accordingly, and have the main text
    field converted to a multi-page field. The import does not import news
    categories. If your new(s) items do not show up in the list, then check
    the language, "include in lists", approval state, and online status of the
    missing items. You must also set the publication list ordering in order to
    sort descending by creation date. <emphasis>The import cannot import the
    comments. This is impossible since Pagesetter have no notion of a
    "comment". It only knows "Hooks" which can be used, among other things,
    for comments.</emphasis></para>
    </section>

    <section id="extraimportce">
    <title>Importing From ContentExpress</title>

    <para>Pagesetter also offers the possibility to import all of your
    ContentExpress pages into a new publication type. Select Tools::Import from
    the menu. Then click on the "Import ContentExpress" button and you are
    done! The new publication type will be named CE, comes with some
    predefined templates (<emphasis>full</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>print</emphasis>) named accordingly, and have the main text
    field converted to a multi-page field. The import does not import
    categories. If your new items do not show up in the list, then check the
    language, "include in lists", approval state, and online status of the
    missing items.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="extraimportpc">
      <title>Importing From PostCalendar</title>

      <para>The PostCalendar import is still a bit experimental. It can copy most of the
      data from PostCalendar into Pagesetter, except for the categories, which you
      will have to add afterwards. The templates can be found in 
      <filename>pagesetter/examples/postcalendar</filename>. It has only been tested with
      PostCalendar version 4.1.0.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="extraimporting">
    <title>Importing Pagesetter Publication Types</title>

    <para>Pagesetter can read a publication type configuration from an
    uploaded XML file and create a new publication type based on that data.
    Beware that a <emphasis>new</emphasis> publication type is created from the
    file, and any categories found in the XML file will also be created as
    <emphasis>new</emphasis> categories. So the current implementation does
    not allow you to update an existing publication type. Select Tools::Import
    from the menu. Then select an XML schema file to upload and click "Import
    XML Schema".</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="extraexporting">
    <title>Exporting Pagesetter Publication Types</title>

    <para>With Pagesetter you can export the setup of a publication type as an
    XML file. This file will be self-containing with both the publication
    setup and the categories needed for it. Select Tools::Export to create the
    export file.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>