<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY mdash "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
]>

<chapter id="chap_introduction">
  <!-- $Id: GuppyDev_Introduction.xml,v 1.2 2005/01/15 21:30:37 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="guppyintrostart">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Guppy framework is a web forms handling system that adds a few
    extra features to the standard HTML forms handling. It allows the
    programmer to specify a web form using a few XML files&mdash;two for each
    form (plus an additional PHP handler file). The use of a relatively simple
    XML specification removes the burden of creating a lot of complex HTML and
    JavaScript from the programmer at the cost of design flexibility.</para>

    <para>With Guppy one can design different <emphasis>components</emphasis>:
    <emphasis>cards</emphasis> that show a single record,
    <emphasis>tables</emphasis> that show multiple records, and
    <emphasis>trees</emphasis> that shows multiple nested records. Each kind
    of component may contain one or more <emphasis>fields</emphasis> of
    different kinds. Fields can currently only be <emphasis>input</emphasis>
    fields with support for booleans (checkboxes), integers, reals, dates,
    times, strings, html, and selectors. Most of the input fields can be
    marked as mandatory which forces the user to enter something in the
    field.</para>

    <para>The benefits of Guppy are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Simpler code generation at the cost of design flexibility. There
        is although some overhead when creating a new form. It does require
        the programmer to create three new files for each form.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Automatic input validation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Automatic handling of multi-record entries with insertion and
        deletion af new rows.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Automatic handling of multi-record nested entries in a tree
        structure.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Wysiwyg HTML input using HtmlArea.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Date selection using a nice little JavaScript date
        picker.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Separation of form specification and layout enabling "untrusted"
        users to change the layout without being able to influence the actual
        functionality.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Consistent look and feel in all web forms.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>