<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY mdash "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
]>

<chapter id="chap_introduction">
  <!-- $Id: Introduction.xml,v 1.9 2005/07/10 20:53:07 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="introductionstart">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Pagesetter is a publishing
    module that allows the PostNuke users to create web pages from structured data, with the data structure
    and output templates defined by the PostNuke administrator. The goal is
    ultimately to be able to define all the kinds of publications that
    normally require different PostNuke modules. The list includes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis>News</emphasis> items with a headline, teaser text,
        news text, and an associated image.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <emphasis>FAQ</emphasis> items consisting of a question and an
        answer.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <emphasis>Recipes</emphasis> with a title, a list of
        ingredients, and instructions.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <emphasis>Task lists</emphasis>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <emphasis>Course descriptions</emphasis>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <emphasis>Music collections</emphasis>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&hellip; and so on.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Screenshot illustrating a News item constructed with Pagesetter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubTemplate.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>See the <filename>readme.txt</filename> for installation instructions.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="introductionfeatures">
    <title>Features</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        User defined publication types with a variable number of input
        fields of many different kinds.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Templatable output lets the adminstrator layout the publications
        in almost any way he want using PostNuke's pnRender system.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        The what-you-see-is-what-you-get (WYSIWYG) editor htmlArea
        simplifies input&mdash;no need for knowing HTML codes.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Multiple nested categories can be created and used for input fields.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Multi-page entries.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Flexible workflow system with plugins to extend it.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Revision control&mdash;Pagesetter stores the complete history of
        all changes to any publication.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        File uploads can be associated with all publications. With this
        feature you can design your own document management system,
        complete with workflows and revision control, or just upload
        images with your News items.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Dates can be selected with a built-in date picker.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Top performance with cached output.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Two level approval control of publishing.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Publications can be timed with a start and end date.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        PostNuke homepage can be set to show any list of publications
        you want.
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        Pagesetter is PostNuke hooks compatible which means you can
        enable comments, scoring, Auto-links and many other features with just
        a few clicks.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="introductioninstallation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>Please read the "install.txt" file for instructions.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="introductionfolder">
    <title>Organizing Publications</title>

    <para>Pagesetter publications can be organized in a folder structure with the
    help of another module "Folder" from www.elfisk.dk. Without this module you
    can browse through linear lists of publications with Pagesetter itself.</para>

    <link linkend="pnfeaturesfolder">Read more in the PostNuke Features chapter</link>.
  </section>

  <section id="introductionprinting">
    <title>Printing This Manual</title>

    <para>The CSS styles in the HTML version has been carefully selected to generate
    a nicely formatted printout. This has although only been tested on the
    Internet Explorer 6.0. If you choose to print the manual then please
    remember to set the paper format to A4 portrait. You should have left and
    right margins set to 5mm.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
