<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY mdash "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
]>

<chapter id="chap_tutorial">
  <!-- $Id: Tutorial.xml,v 1.8 2006/05/16 20:30:23 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <section id="tutstart">
    <title>Tutorial</title>

    <para>Let us start with a quick tutorial showing how to setup your very
    first Pagesetter publication. For this we use a News type as an example.
    With this publication type we will be able to write News with a title,
    a short header, full text, and an associated image selected from Mediashare</para>

    <para>Make sure you have admin rights on your PostNuke site and then goto
    the Pagesetter administration page. Here you will see a list of
    publication types. It should look like this:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubTypeList.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>Pagesetter has, as you can see, created a PN-News publication type
    for you already. You can ignore this or use it as a reference for this tutorial.
    When you are finished with the tutorial you should have a publication type more or
    less identical to the predefined.</para>

    <para>Now click "New Publication Type" which will bring you to this
    window where you give a name to your new publication type and then create it:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubTypeCreate1.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>Click "Next" which will bring you to the window below where you can start adding
    the input fields you want for your publication type:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubTypeCreate2.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>Use the green and red +/- symbols to add and delete fields. Make
    sure you name everything exactly as you see it in the image (description
    text is unimportant).</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>The <emphasis>title</emphasis> radio button indicates which field to
    use as title field in the various Pagesetter lists.</listitem>
      <listitem>The <emphasis>mandatory (M)</emphasis> checkbox indicates that the user
      <emphasis>must</emphasis> enter something in the data field.</listitem>
      <listitem>The <emphasis>Searchable (S)</emphasis>
    checkbox selectes which fields to use when searching for something on your
    website.</listitem>
      <listitem>The <emphasis>multiple
    pages (MP)</emphasis> checkbox allows you to define which field the user may
    insert page breaks in. <emphasis>Only one field may be selected for
    multiple pages, but none need to be so.</emphasis> Page breaks can be
    inserted using the editor button for it or inserted manually with a &lt;hr
    class="pagebreak"/&gt; tag. The templating system then ensures the field
    is split into pages separated by that tag.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Click "Next" again and you will get to the last screen where you can select which
    templates you want to create:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubTypeCreate3.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <important>UNCHECK ALL TEMPLATE CHECKBOXES (for this tutorial)!
    Otherwise the nice default PN-News templates will be overwritten with boring autocreated
    ones!</important>

    <para>The "List Setup" settings
    specify sorting order and such like for this publication type when an
    overview is requested&mdash;for instance when Pagesetter is chosen as the
    frontpage module in PostNuke's admin settings. The sequence of the fields
    does also define the sequence in which they are presented when creating a
    new publication instance. Now you are ready to submit the publication type
    to the database. Press "Commit" and you are done.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tutcreatinst">
    <title>Creating a Publication Instance</title>

    <para>Now that we have a publication type available (News) we should start
    publishing something. Select the "New" link in the publication types
    window:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubTypeList_new.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>This will bring you to the "Publication Edit" window:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubEditData.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>Entering the text should be straight forward. The image URL can be
    selected from Mediashare (if installed) by clicking the "..." button. Now
    press "Save" and you are done and will be brought to the publication
    list:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/pubList.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>If you have named all your fields correctly then you should be able
    to view your new publication through the pre-installed templates. Click
    the <emphasis>view</emphasis> action and you should see:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/publication.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>


    <important>
      <para>You must enable images (with attributes!) and other HTML tags in PostNuke's setup
      before you can display any images. If you forget this then you will only see the text "&lt;img ...&gt;"
      instead of the actual image.</para>
      <para>You must also enable popups for your site if you have any popup blockers installed, otherwise
      HTMLArea and previewing won't work.</para>
      <para>You must also have EZComments installed to get the News example running with the
      templates in the examples directory.</para>
    </important>

  </section>

  <section id="tuttemplates">
    <title>Templates</title>

    <para>The template used to display your data is named
    <filename>PN-News-full.html</filename> and is located in the <filename>pntemplates</filename>
    directory. As you can see the name consists of the
    publication name concatenated with a dash and a template format name (in
    this case "full"). If you open the file you will see something
    like:</para>

    <example>
    <title>Example template for News item.</title>
    <programlisting>
// (the html presented is not the most correct with respect
// to accessibility and xhtml compliancy)
&lt;div style="width: 500px;"&gt;

&lt;div class="pn-title"&gt;&lt;!--[$title]--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="pn-sub"&gt;By: &lt;!--[$core.author]--&gt; 
(&lt;!--[$core.creator]--&gt;) 
&lt;!--[$core.lastUpdated|date_format:"%Y.%m.%d"]--&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td valign="top"&gt;
   &lt;!--[$text[$core.page]]--&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   &lt;!--[if $core.pageCount &gt; 1 ]--&gt;
    Page: &lt;!--[pagesetter_pager]--&gt;
   &lt;!--[/if]--&gt;
  &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td valign="top"&gt;
   &lt;!--[if $image != "" ]--&gt;
     &lt;img src="&lt;!--[$image]--&gt;" width="200" 
          alt="&lt;!--[$imagetext]--&gt;" 
          title="&lt;!--[$imagetext]--&gt;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
     &lt;i&gt;&lt;!--[$imagetext]--&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
   &lt;!--[/if]--&gt;
  &lt;/td&gt;
 &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

&lt;table width="100%"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;!--[$core.printThis]--&gt; | &lt;!--[$core.sendThis]--&gt; 
| Hits: &lt;!--[nocache]--&gt;&lt;!--[$core.hitCount]--&gt;&lt;!--[/nocache]--&gt;
| &lt;!--[nocache]--&gt;&lt;!--[$core.editInfo]--&gt;&lt;!--[/nocache]--&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;!--[if $core.pageCount &gt; 1 ]--&gt;
 &lt;td align="right"&gt;(Page &lt;!--[$core.page+1]--&gt; 
 of &lt;!--[$core.pageCount]--&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;!--[/if]--&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</programlisting>    
    </example>

    <para>The &lt;!--[ ]--&gt; HTML
    comments contain code for the pnRender templating system. Basically you
    can put $fieldName into them to show your publication fields, but more
    complex stuff like switching statements and for-loops can be added too.
    The variable name $core is predefined by Pagesetter and contains core
    information about the publication like author and creation date.
    <emphasis>Do not edit the template directly. Copy it instead to a theme
    specific template and put it into your themes directory as described in
    the template chapter.</emphasis> Read more about templates in the <link
    linkend="chap_templates">Template chapter</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tutfrontpage">
    <title>Putting the News on the Frontpage</title>

    <para>If you want to show your News items on the frontpage of your
    PostNuke installation, you need to find the admin section of PostNuke and
    then go into the settings section. Here you find a dropdown somewhere
    where you can select Pagesetter as the frontpage module. But before that
    you need to tell Pagesetter which publication type to show on the
    frontpage. Go to the general settings of Pagesetter:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/menuGeneral.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>and select the News publication type for the frontpage:</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/configuration.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>If everything goes as expected you should be able to see the News
    list on the frontpage (thanks to <ulink
    url="http://www.postnuke.dk">www.postnuke.dk</ulink> for design
    inspiration):</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="img/publications.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

  </section>
</chapter>