<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap_introduction">
  <!-- $Id: Workflow_Background.xml,v 1.1 2004/12/08 00:29:30 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Background</title>

  <section id="wfbackstart">
    <title>Background</title>

    <section id="wfbackfiles">
      <title>Files and directories</title>

      <para>In the pagesetter/workflows directory, there are two
      subdirectories. Each of these have the same structure.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis>standard</emphasis> directory contains workflow
      information that comes standard with Pagesetter. The
      <emphasis>custom</emphasis> directory contains workflow information that
      you create. Because the Pagesetter workflows are stored in a different
      directory than what you develop, you will never have to worry about an
      upgrade to Pagesetter overwriting your workflow information.</para>

      <para>In the root of the directories are the xml files that define each
      workflow. Under that is an <emphasis>operations</emphasis> subdirectory.
      This directory contains one file for each operation that can be used in
      a workflow action.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="wfbackdepot">
      <title>Depot</title>

      <para>Old revisions of a publication is stored in the
      <emphasis>depot</emphasis>. This revision control means you can always
      go back and view the content of an earlier version of a publication.
      Deleted publications are actually not deleted, but marked deleted and
      then moved to the depot.</para>

      <para>If you really want to delete a document then you can do that while
      browsing the history of a publication, assuming you have admin
      access.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="wfbackstates">
      <title>States</title>

      <para>The state of a publication marks the location of it in the
      workflow process (or rather&mdash;the state machine that the workflow is
      based upon.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="wfbackactions">
      <title>Actions</title>

      <para>Actions are business functions like Submit, Approve, Reject, and
      Delete. They are verbs that can perform operations as well as move a
      document from one state to another. Actions are composed of
      <emphasis>operations</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="wfbackops">
      <title>Operations</title>

      <para>If Actions are business functions then Operations are technical
      functions.</para>

      <para>An operation is a unit of work. Examples are: sending an email,
      deleting a document (moving it to the depot), creating a new revision,
      update publication.</para>

      <para>Operations are individual PHP files that represent one task. Any
      number of these Operations can be used to perform an Action.</para>

      <para>Operations are called from Actions and can be passed parameters if
      necessary.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>