<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap_introduction">
  <!-- $Id: Workflow_WorkflowOperations.xml,v 1.1 2004/12/08 00:29:30 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Workflow Operations</title>

  <section id="wfopintro">
    <title>Workflow Operations</title>

    <para>Workflow operations are the technical bits of the workflow actions.
    In the workflow specification file actions refers to various opearations
    to get things done. An action like "approve" may for instance refer to the
    operations <emphasis>createNewRevision</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>mailToAuthor</emphasis>. Each of these individual operations
    matches precisely one PHP file in the operations directory. The PHP
    operation file is included and after that an interface function in that
    file is called by Pagesetter. If the operation is named
    <emphasis>createNewRevision</emphasis> then the PHP file must be named the
    same&mdash;createNewRevision.php and contain the function
    pagesetter_operation_createNewRevision.</para>

    <para>The interface function is passed a reference to the publication user
    data, a reference to some core data, and the arguments (attributes) of the
    XML operation element in the workflow specification.</para>

    <para>As an example we can take a look at the
    <emphasis>mailNewContentMessage</emphasis> operation: <programlisting>function pagesetter_operation_mailNewContentMessage(&amp;$publication, $core, $args)
{
    // Standard PN-API call that creates a URL to the publication
  $editURL = pnModUrl('pagesetter', 'user', 'pubedit',
                      array('tid'    =&gt; $core['tid'],
                            'id'     =&gt; $core['id'],
                            'action' =&gt; 'edit'));

    // Similar URL creation
  $viewURL = pnModUrl('pagesetter', 'user', 'viewpub',
                      array('tid'    =&gt; $core['tid'],
                            'pid'    =&gt; $core['pid'],
                            'id'     =&gt; $core['id']));

    // Select the arguments specified in the operation tag:
    // &lt;operation message="..." subject="..." recipient="..."&gt;mailNewContentMessage&lt;/operation&gt;
  $message = $args['MESSAGE'] . "\n\nEdit: $editURL\nView: $viewURL";
  $subject = $args['SUBJECT'];
  $mailTo  = $args['RECIPIENT'];

  if (!empty($mailTo))
  {
    $ok = mail($mailTo, $subject, $message);

    if (!$ok)
      return pagesetterWarningWorkflow("Mailing new content to '$mailTo' failed.");
  }

  return pagesetterWFOperationOk;
}</programlisting></para>
  </section>

  <section id="wfoppub">
    <title>The publication Object</title>

    <para>The passed publication object contains the same data as the normal
    templates, except that core values are referred to as core_xxx instead of
    core.xxx.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="wfopcore">
    <title>The core Object</title>

    <para>The core object is not exactly the same as the core object used in
    the templates. For workflows it only contains the tid, pid, id, and
    creatorId values.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="wfopreturn">
    <title>Return Values</title>

    <para>Workflow operations must return one of three values used to inform
    Pagesetter of the result:<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>pagesetterWFOperationOk</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Everything went okay, continue with the workflow
            action.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>pagesetterWFOperationWarning</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Something went wrong, but it was not critial, continue with
            the workflow action. Could for instance be that a mail was not
            sent.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>pagesetterWFOperationError</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Something went so wrong that the workflow action should be
            aborted.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para>In addition to this the operation can call pagesetterWarningWorkflow
    as illustrated in the mail example above. This function sets a warning
    message and returns pagesetterWFOperationWarning. The same goes for a call
    to pagesetterErrorAPI which sets an error message.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>