<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap_introduction">
  <!-- $Id: Workflow_PagesetterWorkflowStructure.xml,v 1.1 2004/12/08 00:29:30 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Pagesetter XML Workflow Structure</title>

  <section id="wfstrucstart">
    <title>Pagesetter XML Workflow Structure</title>

    <para>This section describes the XML elements used in a workflow
    definition. This definition will reside in an XML file in the
    workflows/custom directory.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Title</title>

    <para>A short title for the workflow. This will be used in drop-down
    selection boxes. It will probably be a capitalized version of the xml
    filename.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>A detailed description of what the workflow is and what it does. It
    should explain under what circumstances someone would want to use this
    workflow.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration Settings</title>

    <para>Any information required within this workflow. You will need to
    define this information for each publication type that uses this workflow.
    Examples of configuration settings are notification email addresses. The
    configuration tag includes any number of setting tags. The setting tags
    are defined with an id, title, type, width and height. The possible values
    for the type are "bool", "int", "real", "string", "text" (long string),
    "html" (long string with editor), "date", and "time".</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>States</title>

    <para>A list of all possible states in this workflow. A state is defined
    with an id attribute and the following children. All workflows should at
    least include an 'approved' state with that exact ID.<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A short title for the state (ex: Waiting, Approved). It is
            usually a capitalized version of the state id.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A sentence description of what action was taken to get to
            this state and what action is being waited on (ex: Content has
            been submitted and is waiting for acceptance).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Actions</title>

    <para>A list of all actions that are possible in each state of the
    workflow. An action is defined with an id attribute and the following
    children.<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This title will be used on buttons or in action drop-down
            lists. It is usually a capitalized version of the action
            id.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The action description. This will be available to the user
            as a title (mouse over) text on the action button in the
            publication edit window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Permission</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A boolean expression (predicate) that must evaluate to true
            in order to enable the action. You can refer to the lowest
            Pagesetter permission that is required in order to perform the
            action ("author", "editor", or "moderator"), and you can refer to
            the predicate "owner" which is true or false depending on whether
            or not the current user owns the pubication. A simple permission
            could be &lt;permission&gt;editor&lt;/permission&gt; whereas a
            more advanced one could be &lt;permission&gt;(author and owner) or
            editor&lt;/permission&gt;. The last one is used in the MyWiki
            workflow and states that you must either have at least "editor"
            access or have author access and be the owner of the publication.
            It is possible to combine permission requirements with the usual
            boolean connectors "and" and "or", use "!" for negation, and group
            expressions with parenthetes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>State</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This action is only available when a publication is in this
            state. This is the state id, not the state name.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Operation</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is a list of the Operations that need to take place in
            order to fulfill the requirements of this Action. Parameters can
            be passed to the operation as attributes of the operation's xml
            element.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Online</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The online element is used to change the online flag in the
            document that was edited. It does not affect any new versions of
            the document that are created due to the editing process. To
            affect a new version, use the online="1" attribute when calling
            the operation that creates the new version.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</chapter>