<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap_workflows">
  <!-- $Id: Workflow_Introduction.xml,v 1.2 2004/12/15 22:02:03 jornlind Exp $ -->

  <title>Workflows</title>

  <section id="wfdefinition">
    <title>Definition</title>

    <para>The online Encyclopedia "Wikipedia" describes a workflow like
    this:</para>

    <blockquote>Workflow is the operational aspect of a work procedure:
    how tasks are structured, who performs them, what their relative order is,
    how they are synchronized, how information flows to support the tasks and
    how tasks are being tracked. [WikiPedia <ulink
    url="http://www.wikipedia.org/">www.wikipedia.org</ulink>]</blockquote>

    <para>In Pagesetter we can control where in the workflow a publication is
    located, what kind of actions you can perform on it, when it can be done,
    and who can do it. The location is defined by the publication's state,
    which for instance can be "Preview" for something in preview for an
    editor. The state is something visible and can always be seen on the
    editor's list. The actions can be things like "Submit", "Accept", or
    "Reject", all of which triggers some code that modifies the publication. A
    publication can only change state as a result of a workflow action. You
    never edit the state directly.</para>

    <para>Each of the workflows may have some <emphasis>configuration
    settings</emphasis> that can be set through the menu
    Configuration::Workflow. The standard settings are things related to
    notification mails to be sent when a publication changes state during the
    workflow. The most obvious of these are the mail addresses of the editors
    and moderators that should be informed of new content arrivals.</para>

    <para>The workflow system has been designed to let the administrator add
    his own workflow without modifying the existing ones. This is done through
    an XML file in the "workflows/custom" directory. A thorough description of
    how this is done can be found in the Workflow Manual bundled with this
    manual.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Remember that, no matter how clever a workflow you might
    create, everything begins and ends with your editors. The workflow in it
    self is only a technology, it is not and will never be a substitute for
    good writers.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="wfstandardwfstart">
    <title>Standard workflows</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>None</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allows Authors to create pre-approved documents. Not much to
          this one.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Standard</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allows Authors to submit a publication. It then requires an
          Editor to approve it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enterprise</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Adds an additional approval step to the Standard workflow. An
          Author submits. An Editor accepts or rejects. A Moderator approves
          or rejects. A Moderator can also take publications offline and then
          put them back online.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Wiki</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This workflow gives Authors full access to the publications.
          Every time someone updates a publication, a new version is built and
          a notification email is sent. All changes to all publications are
          logged. Every document is pre-approved. The use of Wiki for the name
          refers to the "edit-by-all" and revision control features. There is
          no support for the normal Wiki notations like using !/!!/!!! for
          headlines .</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>MyWiki</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This workflow gives Authors full access to <emphasis>their
          own</emphasis> publications only. Every time someone updates a
          publication, a new version is built. All changes to all publications
          are logged. Every document is pre-approved. No reason to mail
          someone since it is assumed that you edit your own pages only. This
          is the workflow you should use if you want to allow your users to
          have their own set of pages they can manage. If for instance you
          have a home-garden site and want you users to present their gardens
          on your site then do as follows:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Create a publication type named "Gardens" (or similar) and
              add the fields you need.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Assign the "MyWiki" workflow to this publication
              type.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Check (enable) the access to editing of own pages.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Make sure your users have "author" access to this
              publication type. This can be done with a permission line in
              PostNuke like this: "YourGroup | pagesetter:: | T:: | Edit"
              (where T = type ID).</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para>With this setup your users should be able to create new pages
          as well as edit their own pages only. You need to give them a URL to
          the "edit publication" feature (see the <link
          linkend="chap_linking">linking</link> section).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</chapter>